Finding Aid for Barbara C. Aswad Papers 1962-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Barbara C. Aswad Papers 1962-2000 1975-2000
Aswad, Barbara C.
2 linear feet
Professor of anthropology at Wayne State University, active in issues and organizations specific to the Arab-American population of southeastern Michigan, particularly Dearborn, Michigan. Topical files document Arab and Arab-American culture and life. Organizational files document Aswad's involvement in such organizations as the Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services and the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee.
0227 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was the gift of Barbara Aswad (donor no. 9153 ) and came to the library in 2001.
The collection is open for research.
Dr. Barbara C. Aswad was born in 1936. She received her Ph.D. in Anthropology from the University of Michigan and began teaching at Wayne State University in 1968. She has been involved in issues involving the Arab-American population of southeastern Michigan and has contributed greatly to the development of community-based organizations, particularly in the city of Dearborn, Michigan. She is also a well-known scholar of Middle Eastern cultural anthropology and urban anthropology of the Detroit area's Arab community.
Dr. Aswad's devotion to the Arab community is shown through her activities in a number of organizations. She served on the executive board of the Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services (ACCESS), an organization located in Dearborn since its founding 1971. During the "Southend Struggle," an organized attempt by the City of Dearborn to displace Arab-American residents, she was highly involved with the Southeast Dearborn Community Council. She has also been president of the Middle East Studies Association of North America, a national organization that focuses on scholarship of the Middle East, North Africa, and the Islamic world. She has also been on the Executive Committee of the Middle East Studies Association of the American Anthropological Association.
Dr. Aswad retired from teaching at Wayne State University in 2001 but is still active in the Arab-American community of metropolitan Detroit.
The papers of Barbara Aswad consist primarily of materials relating to her involvement and activism within the Arab-American communities of metropolitan Detroit. The bulk of the collection chronicles her associations with both national and community-based Arab-American organizations, most notably the Arab-American Community Center for Economic and Social Services (ACCESS) of Dearborn, Michigan. The collection has been divided into two series: Topical and Organizations.
Subjects:
American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee.; Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services.; Arab Americans--Michigan.; Arab Americans--Michigan--Dearborn.; Aswad, Barbara C.; Dearborn (Mich.)
- Topical
  The Topical series (1962-1996; 1 linear foot) contains a wide variety of materials, including information on Arab culture and religion, related clippings, education and research connected to the Arab-American community, and materials connected to the city of Dearborn, Michigan. The bulk of this series consists of papers or reports about the Arab-American communities of metropolitan Detroit, many of which were written by former students or colleagues of Aswad.
  - Arab Culture and Religion, 1962-1993 (Box 1)
  - City of Dearborn, 1967-1975 (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - City of Dearborn, 1971-1980 (Box 1)
    - Discrimination, 1977-1986 (Box 1)
    - Immigrants, 1976-1986 (Box 1)
    - Islam, 1989-1994 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1977-1993 (Box 1)
    - Palestinians, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Education and Research
    - Al-Qazzaz, Ayad (Box 1)
    - Aswad, Barbara
      - General (Box 1)
      - MESA Speech, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Bisharat, Mary, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Bowker, Joan, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Ferriel, Kathryn, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Hoffman, Frederick W., 1979 (Box 1)
    - Macki, Norma, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Naff, Alixa (Box 1)
    - Penchansky, Roy, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Smith, Mike, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Stockton, Ronald R., 1975 (Box 1)
    - Suleiman, Michael W. (Box 1)
    - Swank, Jon, 1978 (Box 1)
    - United Community Services of Metropolitan Detroit, 1975-1985 (Box 1)
    - Wolf, Eleanor P., 1966 (Box 1)
    - Yeraka, Sarah, 1994 (Box 1)
- Organizations
  The Organizations series (1967-2000; 1 linear foot) documents Aswad's involvement in various local and national Arab-American groups. These organizations include the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC), the Arab Community Center for Economics and Social Services (ACCESS), the Arabic Outreach Program of Wayne County Community College, the Association of Arab American University Graduates (AAUG), the (Detroit) Islamic Center of America, the Middle East Studies Association (MESA) and the Southeast Dearborn Community Council (SEDCC). Topics covered include activism surrounding the "Southend Struggle," a City of Dearborn, Michigan effort to displace Arab-Americans, community outreach on health issues, and both the internal and external activities of ACCESS.
  - American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC), 1988-1999 (Box 2)
  - Arab Community Center for Economics and Social Services (ACCESS)
    - 1975-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1989 (Box 2)
    - 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2)
    - 1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
    - 1998 (Box 2)
    - 1999 (Box 2)
    - 2000, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Pamphlets (Box 2)
  - Arabic Outreach Program, Wayne County Community College, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Association of Arab American University Graduates, 1971-1978 (Box 2)
  - Islamic Center of America, 1978-1996 (Box 2)
  - Middle East Studies Association, 1985-1992 (Box 2)
  - Southeast Dearborn Community Council, 1967-1977 (Box 2)